Are you paying attention?
Good.
If you're not listening carefully,
you will miss things,
important things.
I will not pause. I will not repeat myself,
and you will not interrupt me.
You think that because you are sitting
where you are and I am sitting where I am
that you are in control
of what is about to happen.
You're mistaken. I am in control.
Because I know things
that you do not know.
Manchester Police Department,
please hold.
Windows broken. Home's been ransacked.
Send a detective down, will you?
What I will need from you now
is a commitment.
You will listen closely, and you
will not judge me until I am finished.
If you cannot commit to this,
then please leave the room.
Come in.
But if you choose to stay,
remember you chose to be here.
What happens from this moment forwards
is not my responsibility.
It's yours.
Pay attention.
- What's all this, then?
- Turing, Alan. Professor at King's.
- Seems there's been a burglary.
- Oh? What of?
Well, that's just it.
Nothing missing, really.
What's he doing in Manchester?
Something with machines.
The project at the NPL.
I checked,
but he won't say what it's on.
Professor Turing?
Detective Nock, Manchester Police.
Sergeant Staehl here tells me
you had a burglary last night.
Professor Turing?
Take a step back,
and don't breath heavily.
- Breathe?
- Undiluted cyanide.
It wouldn't take more
than a thimbleful to kill you.
- Disappointing.
- Pardon?
I had hoped for a bit more.
Sergeant Staehl, is it just me, or do you
get the sense that we're being insulted?
Last night, you had a break-in.
Your neighbor, Mr. Springborn,
called to report the noise.
He said there was quite a ruckus.
Only you say nothing was taken.
It's odd. So, how about you
tell us what happened,
and we'll find the chap who did this.
Gentlemen, I don't believe that
you could find the chap that did this
if he walked up to you
and spat in your face.
What I could us right now is not
a bobby, but a really good cleaning lady.
So, unless one of you
has an apron in your car,
I suggest you file your reports
and leave me alone.
As you say, Professor Turing.
Best of luck with your cyanide.
I'll give you a quid if you can
name me a more insufferable sod.
- Seemed a bit forced, though, didn't it?
- Don't know what you mean.
Well, if you didn't want a pair of bobbies
digging around in your personal affairs,
that'd have been a stellar way
to make sure they don't.
- Tell me you don't think this is suspicious.
- I don't think this is suspicious.
A mysterious professor who won't admit
he's had something stolen from his house?
I think Alan Turing's hiding something.
War declared!
800,000 children evacuated!
German bombs on their way!
Get your papers here!
Fresh off the press! War declared!
800,000 children evacuated!
German bombs expected soon!
This morning,
the British Ambassador in Berlin
handed the German government
a final note stating
that unless we heard from them,
by 11:00, a state of war
would exist between us.
I have to tell you now that no such
undertaking has been received.
And that, consequently,
this country is at war
with Germany.
For the second time
in the lives of most of us,
we are...
at war.
To find
a peaceful way out...
Papers, please.
What are you doing here?
- Oh, the lady told me to wait.
- In my office?
She tell you to help yourself
to tea while you were here?
No, she didn't.
She obviously didn't tell you
what a joke was, then, either, I gather.
Was she supposed to?
- Who are you?
- Alan Turing.
Turing. The mathematician.
- Correct.
- However could I have guessed?
Well, you didn't. You just
read it on that piece of paper.
King's College, Cambridge.
Now, it says here you were a bit of
a prodigy in the maths department.
I'm not sure I can
evaluate that, Mr....
- How old are you, Mr. Turing?
- 27.
And how old were you when you became
a Fellow at Cambridge?
- 24.
- And how old were you...
when you published this paper
that has a title I can barely understand?
23.
And you don't think that qualifies you
as a certified prodigy?
Well, Newton discovered
binomial theorem aged 22.
Einstein wrote four papers that changed
the world by the age of 26.
As far as I can tell, I've...
I've barely made par.
- My God, you're serious.
- Would you prefer I made a joke?
Oh, I don't think you know
what those are.
Hardly seems fair that that's a
requirement for employment here, Mr...
Commander Denniston, Royal Navy.
All right, Mr. Turing, I'll bite.
Why do you wish to work
for His Majesty's government?
Oh, I don't, really.
Are you a bleeding pacifist?
I'm... agnostic about violence.
Well, you do realize
that 600 miles away from London
there's this nasty little chap called Hitler
who wants to engulf Europe in tyranny?
- Politics isn't really my area of expertise.
- Really?
Well, I believe you've just set the record
for the shortest job interview
in British military history.
Mother says I can be
off-putting sometimes
on account of being one of the best
mathematicians in the world.
- In the world?
- Oh, yes.
Do you know how many people
I've rejected for this program?
No.
Well, that's right,
because we're a top-secret program.
But I'll tell you,
just because we're friends,
that only last week, I rejected one
of our great nation's top linguists.
Knows German better than Bertolt Brecht.